Guide to the Dodd, Mead & Company Records 1720-1986 MS 171
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. Publication Records, 1890s-1980s; 20.25 Linear feet
  - Subseries IV.A. Author Contract Summaries, 1890s-1970s; 6.5 Linear feet
    The subseries includes files of cards by title summarizing the contract terms for that title. (The contracts themselves are not in the collection.) There are some variations in the pre-printed forms used, with one used until about 1920, then another used through the end of the date range. The earlier form has somewhat less data fields than the later form. Overall, though, the summaries allow for various data including basic description (e.g., number of words/length, format, date of publication, dates contract was sent and the signed copy received, etc.); compensation data (royalties and payment terms, advance information, price of publication, etc.); and rights information (name under copyright, serial rights ownership, publication plans, international (including Canadian) rights, media rights, use of illustrations, etc.). Although the pre-printed cards include these fields and others for granular detail, only those fields relevant to a contract are completed.
    The cards are in three sets, with the first two similar in content, differing only in that they generally relate to different time periods. The bulk dates of the first are 1890s to 1930s and the second set are 1930s to 1970s, but there is overlap. The third set also summarizes contracts, but appears to be oriented more to royalties and other payments related to reprintings, with notes on actual payments.
    The subseries is arranged by the three sets noted above. Within each set, the cards are arranged alphabetically by author. There are cards for each title by a particular author.
    - Set 1: Author Contract Summaries (1 of 2), 1890s-1940s (Offsite-box 1)
      This box holds records for authors A-K. For this box and the next, the date range is based on the contract dates viewed on a skim of the cards. Bulk dates appear to be 1900s-1930s. Entries of subsequent events/transactions on the cards appear to extend in some cases to the 1960s.
    - Set 1: Author Contract Summaries (2 of 2), 1890s-1940s (Offsite-box 2)
      This box holds records for authors L-W.
    - Set 2: Author Contract Summaries (1 of 3), 1910s-1970s (Offsite-box 3)
      This box holds records for authors A-K. For this box and the next, the date range is based on the contract dates viewed on a skim of the cards. Bulk dates are 1930s-1970s, but a few earlier dates were seen in this set as well.
    - Set 2: Author Contract Summaries (2 of 3), 1910s-1970s (Offsite-box 4)
      This box holds records for authors K-Z.
    - Set 2: Author Contract Summaries (3 of 3). Textbooks, 1950s-1970s (Offsite-box 7)
    - Set 3: Author Contract Summaries (1 of 2), 1920s-1970s (Offsite-box 5)
      This box holds authors A-R. Bulk dates are 1940s-1960s.
    - Set 3: Author Contract Summaries (2 of 2), 1920s-1970s (Offsite-box 6)
      This box holds authors S-Z. Bulk dates are 1940s-1960s.
  - Subseries IV.B. Copyright Records, 1890s-1960; 2.75 Linear feet
    This subseries consists largely of copyright cards that provide both the copyright number used by the Library of Congress and the date filed and renewed, among other information. Over the course of Dodd, Mead's operations and acquisitions of various companies they updated these cards and their arrangements several times, with some series organized alphabetically or by renewal date on index cards and others in ledgers chronologically. The original organization of each of these groups of records was maintained.
    Arranged by format.
    - Copyright Logbooks, 1896-1960 (Offsite-box 26)
      There are gaps in the date range. Specific ranges of the volumes are 1896-1898, 1901-1910, 1916-1960.
    - Copyright Cards, 1890-1940s (Offsite-box 9)
      This box contains Library of Congress copyright acknowledgement cards, sorted alphabetically by author from the late 1800s through the 1940s. The cards are divided into three index card size boxes: A-G, H-P, P-Z. The box contains two additional index card size boxes. These additional boxes have subjects with corresponding partial quotes from a specified book (their organization and purpose is unclear and uncontextualized).
    - Copyright Cards, 1904-1936 (Offsite-box 8)
      This box contains four index card size boxes of Library of Congress copyright cards sorted by year renewed or not renewed. Each box contains a year range in alphabetical order: 1904-1909; 1910-1914; 1915-1923; 1924-1936. The box also contains two additional index card size boxes. One of these contains disorganized Library of Congress copyright cards as well as Agatha Christie title cards. The other contains semi-alphabetically arranged Library of Congress copyright cards by author (ostensibly from rights acquisition via another publisher) as well as more Agatha Christie title cards.
  - Subseries IV.C. Printing Inventories, 1920s-1980s; 11 Linear feet
    This subseries contains two sets of printing records on cards. The first set spans from 1920s-1940s and the second from the 1950s-1980s. While the physical format of the two sets differ, they each contain similar information concerning the printing specifications of the book (whether there are illustrations, etc.) and how many were printed.
    Arranged in two date range-based sets and alphabetically by title within each set.
    - Printing Inventories (Titles A-C), 1920-1940s (Offsite-box 35)
    - Printing Inventories (Titles C-G), 1920-1940s (Offsite-box 36)
    - Printing Inventories (Titles G-L), 1920-1940s (Offsite-box 37)
      International Classics Series included.
    - Printing Inventories (Titles L-P), 1920-1940s (Offsite-box 38)
    - Printing Inventories (Titles P-T), 1920-1940s (Offsite-box 39)
    - Printing Inventories (Titles T-Z), 1920-1940s (Offsite-box 40)
      Includes Collector Series (in alphabetical order) and Elsie
    - Printing Inventories A (ABC of Boat Sailing) - B (Better Golf For Boys), 1950-1980s (Offsite-box 41)
    - Printing Inventories B (Better Gymnastics For Boys) - C (Creative Mind), 1950-1980s (Offsite-box 42)
    - Printing Inventories D (Dan Barry's Daughter) - F (Famous Twentieth Century Leaders), 1950-1980s (Offsite-box 43)
    - Printing Inventories F (Famous Underwater Adventures) - H (How Super Highways are Made), 1950-1980s (Offsite-box 44)
    - Printing Inventories H (How they Blazed the Way) - L (Lyrics of a Low Brow), 1950-1980s (Offsite-box 45)
    - Printing Inventories M (The Mackin Cover) - O (1001 Christmas Fact and Fan Fancies), 1950-1980s (Offsite-box 46)
    - Printing Inventories O (1001 Garden Questions Answered) -S (Scrambling Quarterback), 1950-1980s (Offsite-box 47)
    - Printing Inventories S (Scratch a Lover) - T (Taming of Carney Wilde), 1950-1980s (Offsite-box 48)
    - Printing Inventories T (Tamer Lane) - W (What Does a Coast Guardsman Do?), 1950-1980s (Offsite-box 49)
    - Printing Inventories W (What Does a Coastguardsman Do) - Z (Zuleika Dobson), 1950-1980s (Offsite-box 50)
- Series V. Biographical and Company History Documents, 1834-1975; .76 Linear feet
  This series consists of photographs, newspaper clippings, biographical notes, end of life planning notes and other miscellaneous documents concerning the family and leadership of Dodd, Mead. The various documents are foldered together as found in the collection.
  Arranged by format with photographs first, followed by the miscellaneous documents in a rough alphabetical order by folder label. Labels in "quotation marks" are transcribed from original folders and envelopes; others were established by the processing archivist.
  - Photograph of Company/Family, 19th/20th Century (Offsite-box 28, Folder 2)
  - Photograph of Edward H. Dodd Sr., 20th century (Offsite-box 51, Folder 30)
  - Photograph of Moses Dodd, 19th century (Offsite-box 28, Folder 10)
  - Photograph of Moses Dodd, 19th century (Offsite-box 28, Folder 13)
  - Photograph of Moses Dodd, 19th century (Offsite-box 51, Folder 14)
  - Photographs (4) of Moses Dodd, 19th century (Offsite-box 28, Folder 1)
  - Photographs (cabinet cards) of Mr. and Mrs. Moses Dodd, 19th century (Offsite-box 51, Folder 42)
    Three of Mr. and seven of Mrs. Moses Dodd taken and/or printed by Rockwood Instantaneous Photographs.
  - Photograph of Robert H. Dodd, 20th century (Offsite-box 51, Folder 1)
    Also includes negative.
  - Typescript of Autobiographical Sketch of Moses Dodd, 19th century (Offsite-box 51, Folder 5)
  - Biographical Materials of Frank C. Dodd, 1939 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 40)
    Includes: biographical material (copies and drafts), end of life planning correspondence (between Doe Band and Fred Slota), death announcement, obituary, 7 headshots and negative, obituary clippings from various newspapers, the Saturday Review of Literature 1939 Vol. XXI No. 5.
  - Dodd, Mead in the Press and Assorted Material, 1905-1938 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 12)
    Originally titled "colophons" the folder only includes one colophon. The rest includes: A historical pamphlet on the Brick Church (1928); Herald Tribune feature of Dodd, Mead (1936); Ella Hardcastle obituary clippings; "books and things" clippings; correspondence concerning good press for Dodd, Mead (1938); 2 sets of speech notecards and a speech draft for a dinner at the Rockefeller Association; New York Evening Post clipping (1916); correspondence from an unspecified uncle to Mr. Dodd (1939); British Weekly clippings (1916); Frank H. Dodd feature in New York Evening Post (1916); Philadelphia Press Book Magazine clippings (1916); McClury's Book News clippings of October 1964 for the 125th anniversary announcement; the New International Bulletin (1905); placard with unknown signature.
  - Folder "EHD", 1916-1975 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 35)
    Includes: Frank Dodd biographical material; Herald Tribune Book News (1939); The Evening Post (1916) + photocopy; The Evening Post (1918); The Daily News (1975); Publisher's Weekly (1975); The Best Plays Series Sales and Inventory; Bestseller list (1975); New York Times clippings; Rutherford Platt obituary; Price increases list (1975), Memorandum; Minutes of staff meeting (1975).
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1916 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 34)
    Includes: New York Evening Post, January 15, 1916; Philadelphia Press Book Magazine, April 9, 1916; British Weekly, January 20, 1916; Literary Digest International Book Review (Dodd, Mead feature).
  - Miscellaneous, 1872-1927 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 36)
    Includes: a new books list (1872); Publisher's Weekly clipping (1927); Moses Dodd biographical papers.
  - Folder of "Possible Portfolio Material", 1834-1899 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 16)
    Includes photographs: Mr. and Mrs. Moses Dodd in Canada (Niagara Falls) and Moses Dodd; advertisements: reproduction of printing press ad (1834); Dodd, Mead ad featuring the Brick Church, (the original office of Dodd, Mead) (1848); new book releases ad (1899); bestseller ad "Ten Successes"; "Popular and Important Books" ad; "A Discourse on the Moral Uses of the Sea" title page reproduction; copy of correspondence between Paul Lawrence Dunbar and a Mr. Howells (in which the kindness of Mr. Dodd, most likely Moses Dodd, is praised); newspaper copy about E. P. Roe book release "Without a Home" (1881).
  - Folder "Triton Logbook", 1916 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 41)
    Includes: Philadelphia Press Book Magazine (1916); Dodd, Mead History booklet; Vanderbilt Hotel note; 506 Broadway Photograph; office photograph (1916); photograph of 5th and 21st Street; Lower Manhattan map; 5 East 19th Street photograph by PL Sperr; East side of 5th and 21st Street by PL Sperr; 751 Broadway photo by PL Sperr.
  - Retirement Honorarium Plaque to Frank C. Dodd (former president) on behalf of the National Association of Book Publishers, 1929 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 13)
- Series VI. Books and Other Publications, 1720-1938; 3 Linear feet
  This subseries contains all the books and non-promotional publications in the Dodd, Mead records. The books in this series largely have a religious focus and most, though not all (some date to the 1700s), were published by Dodd, Mead in their first few decades. Most of the books include a name, inscription, or other markings on a flyleaf or other front page. These tend to suggest that many of these books were acquired secondhand, such as through used book stores. A couple were inscribed with the name Stephen Dodd and these were noted in the container list.
  Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - "Memoir and Sermons" by Reverend Wm. J. Armstrong, D.D., 1853 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "The Christian Retrospect and Register" by Robert Baird, 1851 (Offsite-box 11)
  - "The Value of the Soul" By Rev. J. Batey, 1849 (Offsite-box 11)
  - "The Westminster Shorter Catechism" Rev. James R. Boyd, 1854 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "Millennarian Views" by Alfred Bryant, 1852 (Offsite-box 12)
  - "Chronicles of the Schonberg-Cotta Family" by Elizabeth Charles, 1864 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "Chronicles of the Schonberg-Cotta Family" By Elizabeth Charles, 1864 (Offsite-box 12)
  - "Diary of Mrs. Kitty Trevylyan" by Elizabeth Charles, 1864 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "Diary of Mrs. Kitty Trevylyan" by Elizabeth Charles, 1864 (Offsite-box 11)
  - "The Early Dawn" by Elizabeth Charles, 1864 (Offsite-box 11)
  - "The Early Dawn" by Elizabeth Charles, 1864 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "Is Christianity From God?" by Rev. John Cumming D. D., 1849 (Offsite-box 12)
  - "Is Christianity From God?" by Rev. John Cumming, D.D., 1849 (Offsite-box 12)
  - "The Memoir of Mrs. Elizabeth B. Dwight" by H.G.O. Dwight, 1840 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "History of Redemption" by Jonathan Edwards, 1793 (Offsite-box 10)
    Inscribed "Stephen Dodd, 1804"
  - "The Life and Experience of Rev. Jonathan Edwards", 1804 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "The Old Chest and Its Treasures" by Aunt Elizabeth, 1859 (Offsite-box 12)
  - "Works of Charlotte Elizabeth" by Charlotte Elizabeth, 1845 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "Brewer's Family" by Mrs. Ellis, 1867 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "True Cause of All Contention, Strife, and Civil War in Christian Communities" by Rev. D. C. Hopkins, A. M., 1862 (Offsite-box 12)
  - "Behind the Skyline: A Pictorial Study of Downtown New York" by Huntington Corporation, 1938 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 15)
  - "An Earnest Ministry the Want of the Times" by John Angell James, 1848 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "An Earnest Ministry the Want of the Times" (reprint) by John Angell James, 1860 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "The Churches and Pastors of Washington D. C." by Lorenzo D. Johnson, 1857 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "The Autobiography and Ministerial Life of the Rev. John Johnston, D.D." Edited and Compiled by the Rev. James Carnahan, D.D., 1856 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "The Autobiography and Ministerial Life of The Rev. John Johnston, D.D." by The Rev. James Carnahan, D.D., 1856 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "Memoir of Asahel Grant, M.D." by Rev. A. C. Lathrop, 1847 (Offsite-box 12)
  - "The Plenary Inspiration" by Eleazar Lord, 1857 (Offsite-box 12)
  - "The Book of Ecclesiastes Explained" by James M. MacDonald, D.D., 1856 (Offsite-box 12)
  - "Watchwords of the Warfare of Life" by Dr. Martin Luther, 1869 (Offsite-box 12)
  - "Journal and Letters of the Rev. Henry Martyn, B.D.", 1851 (Offsite-box 12)
  - "The Tree of the Knowledge of Good and Evil" by J.H. M'Ilvaine, 1847 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "Dissertations on the Prophecies" by Thomas Newton D.D., 1794 (Offsite-box 10)
    Inscribed "Stephen Dodd"
  - "The Lectures Complete of Father Gavazzi" by G.B. Nicolini, 1854 (Offsite-box 11)
  - "Memorial of the Life and Service of the Late Rev. Henry A. Rowland, D.D." by E.R. Fairchild, D.D., 1860 (Offsite-box 11)
  - "The Path of Life" by Henry A. Rowland, 1861 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "Scripture Manual" by Charles Simmons, 1845 (Offsite-box 10)
    Proof Text
  - "Sermons of Rev. Ichabod S. Spencer, Vol I" by Rev. J.M. Sherwood, 1855 (Offsite-box 12)
    Inscribed by a Dodd to his father, 1856.
  - "Sermons of Rev. Ichabod S. Spencer, D.D." by Rev. J.M. Sherwood, 1855 (Offsite-box 12)
  - "A Pastor's Sketches" by Ichabod S. Spencer, D.D., 1851 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "Sermons of Rev. Ichabod S. Spencer, D.D. ", 1855 (Offsite-box 12)
  - "A Pastor's Sketches" by Ichabod S. Spencer, D.D., 1855 (Offsite-box 11)
  - "A Pastor's Sketches" by Ichabod S. Spencer, D. D., 1856 (Offsite-box 12)
  - "A Pastor's Sketches" by Ichabod S. Spencer, D.D., 1857 (Offsite-box 12)
  - "The Attraction of the Cross" by Gardiner Spring, D.D., 1846 (Offsite-box 11)
  - "The Attraction of the Cross" by Gardiner Spring, D.D., 1845 (Offsite-box 11)
  - "The Mercy Seat" by Gardiner Spring, D.D., 1850 (Offsite-box 11)
  - "The Glory of Christ" by Gardiner Spring, 1852 (Offsite-box 11)
  - "The Bible Not of Man" by By Gardiner Spring, D.D., 1847 (Offsite-box 11)
  - "A History of Division of the Presbyterian Church in the United States of America" by a Committee of the Synod, 1852 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "Spiritual Heroes; or, Sketches of the Puritans" by John Stoughton, 1850 (Offsite-box 11)
  - "Commentary on the Book of Proverbs" by Moses Stuart, 1857 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "Apostolic Baptism" by C. Taylor, 1850 (Offsite-box 11)
  - "Thinks-I-To-Myself: Serio - Ludicro, Tragico - Comico Tale" by Thinks-I-To-Myself Who, 1843 (Offsite-box 11)
  - "Life of Charlotte Elizabeth" by L.H.J. Tonna, 1851 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "Eight Sermons Prech'd at the Cathedral Church of St. Paul" by Dan Waterland, D.D., 1720 (Offsite-box 12)
    Inscribed by a Dodd in 1869.
  - "History of the Township of Mount Pleasant, Wayne County, Pennsylvania" by Rev. Samuel Whaley, 1856 (Offsite-box 12)
  - "Letters to a Millenarian" by Rev. A. Williamson, 1852 (Offsite-box 10)
  - "The Works of Leonard Woods, D. D." by Leonard Woods, D.D., 1849 (Offsite-box 11)
  - "The New International Bulletin", 1904-1906 (Offsite-box 51, Folder 8)
    13 copies of The International Bulletin: November 1904 (2); July 1905 (4); June 1906 (6); July 1906 (1).
  - "The Whole Book of Psalms." Reproduction of 1640 Title Page, 1929 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 13)
    Number 114 of 200. Printed by Harpers Magazine.
  - "The Female Jesuit; or, The Spy in the Family", 1851 (Offsite-box 11)